[Music]
well welcome to true news on Rick Wiles
if space aliens landed in America and
visited Evangelical Protestant churches
and watch Christian television and
listen to Christian radio and read
Christian books
the Martians would think that millions
of Americans belong to something called
the rapture religion and that they
worship a god named Israel it would be
unlikely
the Martians would hear anything about
Jesus Christ the cross salvation
Holiness the glorious appearing and the
resurrection of the Dead and eternity in
New Jerusalem slowly over decades the
American evangelical Protestant faith
has been transformed into Babylonian
churchianity they departed the ancient
Christian faith and they started a new
religion they replace the Christian
cross with the occult Star of David
sadly millions of Americans don't even
realize that the true Christian faith
centered on Jesus Christ has been
swapped out for a fake faith centered on
Israel's land now it didn't happen
overnight
the deception has been underway for
decades
the growth of religious television radio
and publishing however greatly advanced
the propaganda how did we get to this
place in 2018 where millions of people
who go to church don't know the core
tenets of the Christian faith who
hoodwinked them into believing another
gospel Doc perc heart and I are going to
discuss
the origin of the rapture doctrine and
the blasphemous idolizing of the State
of Israel as a god doc I can't put it in
any other words that's what's happened
to Christianity in America and for 1,900
years Rick there was a historic idea of
what the end times would look like what
things would look like here in this day
and age based upon what the Apostles
taught and what the Church Fathers
taught and what was handed down over the
centuries but over the past really the
past 150 but it's specifically the past
100 years that we've seen this seismic
shift in the idea of endtime theology
and what we're going to talk about today
is how did this shift take place in
America because it's in America right
you can go around where you've been a
missionary you know that this doctrine
is not believed it's not even known in
most parts of the world
the only places where the rapture
doctrine and this idolizing of Israel is
known is where American television and
radio has gone or American missionaries
have gone and introduced the doctrine
into other countries but the churches in
Latin America in Europe and Asia in the
Middle East they don't know anything
about it and at the very root of all
this change we talk about in theology
here in the the last hundred fifty
hundred years Rick is adding new
revelation to the Word of God that's
right that's at the core of it adding
something to the word that isn't there
now that's exactly how this all came
about and we're gonna talk about the
origin of it you have to go back to the
1830s yes
Johnny nelson darby yes - in Great
Britain there was a sect called the
Plymouth Brethren and they were a very
radical sect John Nelson Darby was a I
guess he would describe him as a
disgruntled anglican cleric he actually
was pushed out of the yes first out of
the Anglican Communion he he became the
leader of the Plymouth Brethren and they
believed and this is why it's so
dangerous
the Plymouth Brethren and they're still
around today but not much of an
organization of a denomination but their
their doctrine took over the Protestant
churches of America but they believed
that God gave them revelation knowledge
about the last days that the Lord had
not given any other right people in at
that time eighteen hundred years right
of church history so once again it comes
back hey I've heard something I've got
something that no one else has got and
it's adding to the Word of God and that
was their deception they were hearing
their atlas and they were hearing voices
of demons that's really what it was they
were hearing the voices of demons
telling them here is new revelation from
the Word of God that nobody has ever
seen before we're and these were demons
speaking to them and they were believing
they it was God telling them things that
had been kept from the greatest
theologians of the of the church kept
from the apostles think about that yeah
they they were so arrogant as to believe
that they had knowledge that God didn't
even give the apostles West sounds
familiar even today so same stuff going
on today that's right and I don't know
if you know this not but inside the
Plymouth Brethren there was a super
radical sect
all right called the exclusive Brethren
okay all right hey so they were even
more privileged than the regular brother
not first I've heard of that yes Oh John
Nelson Darby was the founder of the
exclusive brother inkay all right he had
even more knowledge than the rest of
them and so they came up with this over
time they came up with us this doctrine
of dispensationalism that God was
dealing with humanity in dispensations
nobody had ever taught this nonsense
right they dreamed a stuff up and they
began to teach it and do you know who
their biggest critic was and in Great
Britain
at that time who it was a pastor named
Charles Spurgeon oh just some
run-of-the-mill pastor yeah yeah the
Reformed Baptist pastor now how would
you like to get called down from the
pulpit of Charles Spurgeon but Charles
Spurgeon was denouncing the Plymouth
Brethren as a dangerous radical sect and
he was warning the Christians of London
stay away from them they're teaching
heresies right and now their heresies
are the accepted teaching of the
Protestant churches in America
so this idea of dispensational in is and
that God operated with man in different
ways and different ages had different
redemptive paths yes yet throughout the
ages nowhere is that taught in Scripture
no we're only taught we've really in
Jesus himself only taught to pass there
was the Old Covenant and there was the
New Covenant that was it
that's right wasn't different ages there
wasn't different time periods or
anything like that
so it seems to me lirik that something
as big as that Jesus himself would have
been addressing and said now listen guys
there were you know seven different ages
throughout time but he only stressed
two ages the age of the Old Covenant and
the age of the New Covenant and the
Apostle Paul didn't see it either did he
no he never mentioned it at any time and
yet Paul had been given perfect
knowledge of the kingdom and so the
brethren under John Nelson Darby they
they concoct it what I have coined the
name
Dipsy ISM D ppz Dipsy ISM the D is for
dispensationalism and then premillennial
right meaning the Christ is going to
reign for a thousand years after he
returns to earth right and then
pre-tribulation he becomes back before
the tribulation period begins yes
secretly for the for the Gentile church
right and then he comes seven years
later again to establish this Jewish
Kingdom in Israel so the you've got
d for Dipsy ISM I had D for
dispensational premillennial preacher
relation and the Z is Zionism because
it's all built around Zionism there was
there there is no purpose for this
doctrine without the propaganda for a
Zionist state it was created for the
establishment of Israel this is the only
reason for this doctorate it's a way
back in the 1800s
so you had two tracks kind of building
you had something building in the in the
church at that time through the Plymouth
Brethren and this new dispensational
idea that was coming about but within
jewelry around the world within the
Jewish faith there was a different path
building up and that was a goal of a
restoration of the State of Israel
that's right at some point and the two
more the same track this who came
together and that's what we're going to
talk about here today so when did it
come together it came together in the
early 1900s
because John Nelson Darby 'he's crazy
doctrines went nowhere they stayed in
Great Britain among the Plymouth brother
and all through the 1800s
and there were only pockets of people in
the United States who even knew about it
that that gave it any kind of of respect
but then there is a Cyrus Scofield and
Scofield became the the propaganda
Meister for John Nelson Darby 's
doctrine but before we get into the
doctrine I want to talk about who Cyrus
Scofield was because this is going to
blow away people if you have a Scofield
reference Bible you need to know the
author of that reference Bible because
he's not the person who think he is he's
not dr. Scofield they raised the dollar
it never was a doctor
all right never ever I'm gonna go down a
list of some things about Cyrus Scofield
okay
so first he embellished his civil war
record he was in the Confederate Army
the seventh Tennessee infantry
he totally embellished his his record
and if you go on the internet you can
find a very detailed investigation by a
Tennessee professor who did a lot of
research into Schofield true military
record and that was a contemporary of
his age that write that wrote it up so
who wrote exactly what Schofield did but
then compared it to what he said about
his record he embellished it
he made up stuff he made people believe
he was a hero he was a hero at Antietam
I mean all kinds of stuff and and
Scofield just made things up but this is
this was typical of his life after
deserting the Confederate Army he was
given safe passage to st. Louis Missouri
right and in 1873 he helped a Jewish
lawyer named John Engels become the US
senator from the state of of Kansas and
what should say senator Engels appointed
Scofield as the US District Attorney for
Kansas right okay Scofield was 29 years
old nice position for 29 he never went
to law school right okay became US
District Attorney for the State of
California's I'd listen to me folks
Cyrus Scofield was forced to resign as
US District Attorney of Kansas under a
cloud of scandal including bribery yes
and laying transfers and yes I'm very
quite and as old money out of people
there were warrants for his
some people believe he served some some
time in jail for forgery
he was forging his forging names to
banknotes to get loans the guy was
involved in all kinds of shady deals
okay this is Cyrus Scofield so where
does he go from there he escaped but he
was always like two steps ahead of the
law right the law was looking for him
but he managed to stay ahead of the
sheriff well he ended up well at that
time he was married he was married to a
woman he had two children and then he
abandoned his wife and children and he
ends up in Dallas Texas and becomes the
pastor of the First Congregational
Church of Dallas now he marries a woman
from the church but he doesn't tell the
church that he abandoned his wife and
children back in in Kansas now he never
gave him a dime in support totally
abandoned them and yet he's a pastor of
a church in Dallas okay and he doesn't
tell the congregation you know he didn't
put that on his resume he didn't tell
the you know the pastor real selection
committee oh by the way I've got another
wife and kids back there in Kansas and I
got this new wife here and he just kept
it quiet okay so 18 let's see what was
at 1883 his wife filed for divorce okay
and filed for on charges of abandonment
right all right
so this is the record of of Cyrus
Scofield well then you know this fast
forward early 1900s now he's a he's a
pastor of a small church I think in
Boston Massachusetts okay it's making
like $1,000 a year salary still going
nowhere well right I mean in terms of
finances and things like that are
easiest he's just a small church pastor
right he gets invited
to become a member of the Lotus Club of
New York City now what's the Lotus Club
well the Lotus Club is one of the most
prestigious gentlemen's club of New York
City we're talking about people you know
sponsors like Andrew Carnegie all right
the elite of the elite were members of
the Lotus Club and is still around today
where did he get the money where did he
get the money to pay the membership dues
the membership dues were more than his
salary right all right
where why would why would he be invited
there's nobody pastor why would he be
invited to come to New York City and
join the Lotus Club well who who
sponsored him who the man who sponsored
Cyrus Scofield was a Jewish lawyer named
Samuel hunted Meyer now Samuel an Tamar
was a agent for the Rothschild banking
dynasty all right so he's the one that's
financing this up to this point
well he's inviting Cyrus Scofield to
join the Lotus Club well I what why
would a lawyer
Samuel unta Meyer an agent for the
Rothschilds what interest would he have
in Cyrus Scofield an unknown
undistinguished pastor of a small church
in Massachusetts who's got a police
record and a shady past for being a
swindler why would this Jewish lawyer
want anything to do with Cyrus Scofield
has learned a little bit more about who
mr. hunt Meyer was he was a zealous
advocate for the Zionist liberation
movement that was in full swing at that
time so they were in the process of
trying to come up ways to reestablish
the nation of Israel that's right not
not on a religious basis no no it looks
strictly this is a goal that we have to
get the land back right okay
mr. an Tamar played a big role in the
election of Woodrow Wilson okay and a
very influential role in convincing
President Wilson to take the USA in the
world war 1 now was mr. Altmire
a really good Christian guy no he was a
Zionist Jewish lawyer so why is a
Zionist Jewish lawyer he interested in
some small town preacher in Boston well
that's immoral isn't that the
million-dollar question here and there's
one one other piece of information you
need to know about mr. an Tamar he is
could remember I told you he was an
agent for the Rothschilds he wrote the
Senate law he wrote the Senate bill that
became law that established the US
Federal Reserve banking systems so this
is the guy that we have to blame him for
the Federal Reserve today he also became
the I guess the first lawyer for the IRS
already I'm not like anyone's okay so
you've got a Zionist leader a Rothschild
agent and definitely a New World Order
person yes so who led the u.s. in the
World War one who was manipulating
woodrow wilson who wrote the senate bill
for the Federal Reserve Act and now he
becomes friends with Cyrus Scofield and
says I want you to join the Lotus Club
well what happens then well Cyrus
Scofield suddenly gets sponsored to go
to London and he has a meeting with the
head people the top executives of Oxford
publishing alright and that was the
premier publishing company in the world
at that time rather believe it and you
just couldn't get a meeting in London
with Oxford publishing but he could yeah
he got him there and he got him over to
he got him over in London to meet with
the Oxford publishing executives and so
Scoville comes back with a con
tract a publishing contract to publish
John Nelson Darby zionists notes in a
Christian Bible gah how does this work
it's called propaganda folks the Zionist
Jews infiltrated the Christian Church in
the early 1900s through Cyrus Scofield
he was their little puppet they
introduced Zionist propaganda into the
churches by publishing Darby's notes in
a Bible so they defiled the Holy Bible
they defiled it they corrupted the Bible
by publishing notes that were promoting
Zionism and so then somebody financed
the publication of a vast number of
Scofield Bibles and suddenly these
things were being mailed out to churches
all over America I remember stories that
my great aunt used to tell me of Bible
salesman back in the 20s and 30s and so
I did a little research on that do you
know the Bible's that they were selling
they were selling Scofield Bibles and so
these Bibles were getting distributed
all over you know rural America small
town church millions million all over
and the Bible salesman would get the
Bibles for free and then they would sell
them for whatever amount that they could
get out of it well how would they get
them for free they the company that was
publishing them obviously wanted to get
their Bibles out there well that was
Oxford that's right
so Oxford gave away the Bibles right Wow
out of the goodness of their heart right
right no they were they were
infiltrating the American evangelical
churches with Zionist propaganda and
slowly all right
the Baptist bought into it right the
Pentecostals bought into it the
Assemblies of God the Church of God just
go down the list of
Pentecostal and Baptist denominations
that got suckered into this thing yeah
and people actually believe the notes
are sacred as the texts that are there
and I can speak to personal experience
from that when I was at Bible College I
had friends that believe the text the
notes they said though this is inspired
as well are you crazy how can the notes
be inspired but there were people that
felt like the notes themselves were
inspired that's right and so now it's
become that the doctrine has become
accepted in thousands of churches in
America you watch Christian television
it's the only thing to hear the rapture
the rapture rapture Israel is or Israel
and if you say anything else
you're the heretic right and even if you
don't use a Scofield Bible or reference
about it has so influenced the
leadership of so many denominations
you know like Moody Bible Institute
Dallas Theological Seminary all these
different places it that's the template
that has been laid on the doctrine in
North America well sorry Scofield was
friends with Dwight Moody
now they split well apparently Dwight
Moody figured out that Cyrus Scofield
was Shady
but moody kept the doctrine right okay
the Scofield people are the ones who
started the Dallas Theological Seminary
and actually mr. Scofield I don't think
was the editor of his Bible yes about
that
Arlo Grable in yes there was a just a
rabbit Zionist a Christian pastor but
man he was he was totally sold out to
getting Israel to get their land back in
play sorry that's all I was just entire
mission okay he speak
he spoke Yiddish better than most Jews
and and so a lot of people think that he
he actually was the the editor of the
Scofield Bible now one thing we
mentioned in the beginning
dr. Scofield
all right he's known today as dr.
Scoville dr. Cyrus Scofield and I would
like right now I want to put out a
challenge to Dallas a Theological
Seminary Moody Bible Institute and all
the other rapture people out there
please send to me the name of the
educational institution where dr. Cyrus
Scofield attended and graduated and was
given a Doctor of Divinity degree please
send me that institutions name because
it doesn't exist and you all know it you
know he is a liar and a scoundrel and
you've kept up the lie because you don't
want the public to know the truth about
Cyrus Scofield but he was not a doctor
of anything a doctor of buffoonery or
Rickon will come down in the last couple
minutes of the program here there's
probably people watching the program
today this the first time they've heard
any of this so they've got this new
information where do they go from here
what do they do with this information
well if you got a Scofield Bible throw
it in the trash that would be the first
thing and just read the Bible without
anybody's no tenant is Jesus this notes
not good enough honestly that's true it
is it's not enough is the word of God
itself not what it is is Jesus not
enough all right just start reading the
Bible without anybody's notes get rid of
all your Bible prophecy books and all
that stuff you got in your charts and
everything and just get on your knees
and read your by I look read your Bible
on your knees
yes all right there's a good it's a good
way to lose your perspective doesn't it
read the Bible on your knees and ask the
Holy Spirit to show you things you know
I know we're down to wow we're just
getting started
I know I got so much I want to talk
about I think doc hour oh wow in the
program with the scripture from
Joshua this is world all the Christian
Zionists who are waiting on God to
fulfill the promises to the Jews to give
them their land back this is Joshua 21
verses 43 thus the Lord gave to Israel
all the land that he swore to give to
their fathers and they took possession
of it and they settled there and the
Lord gave them rest on every side just
as he has sworn to their fathers not one
of all their enemies had withstood them
for the Lord had given all their enemies
into their hands now listen to verse 45
not one word of all the good promises
that the Lord had made to the house of
Israel had failed all came to pass in
other words they're saying in that
passage of Scripture that they possessed
all the land they already had the land
God fulfilled all of his promises to
Israel and they lost the land because of
rebellion and sin against God and now
they want their land back and God isn't
playing that game we're out of time
thank you for watching true news we'll
see you tomorrow
[Music]